Worksheet: C Syntax and Versions

Week 1
Mike Fraser

Below is a simple C program, helloworld.c, which has several mistakes which will prevent it from compiling. These are called 'syntax' errors, meaning that the code does not conform to the required C language syntax. Copy the program into a file and repair it so it compiles and runs. There are 7 problems with the code. Try compiling with the -Wall flag, i.e. gcc -Wall helloworld.c -o helloworld, to see what extra information you receive.

#include <stdioo.h>
#inclde <stdlib.h>

mian(void) {
  printf("Hello")
  printf(World);
  printf("\");
  return 0;
)

You may find the gcc compiler error guide at the following URL useful:

https://www.cs.bris.ac.uk/Teaching/Resources/COMS10002/error.html

There are different C versions, the original ANSI C standard, sometimes called C89, then major revisions in 1999 (C99) and 2011 (C11). Read about this history here:

http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/C_(programming_language)#History

Some features of the C language vary between these different specifications, which means that not all C code is compatible with all C compilers or all other C code. The gcc compiler allows you to pick the version of C you are compiling using the -std= option, e.g. gcc -std=c99 twelve.c -o twelve. Copy the following C code into a file and compile and run it using the C99 standard.

#include <stdio.h>

int main(void) {
// Calculate 3*4 and print the result
    printf("3*4=%d", 3*4);
    return 0;
}

The first line beginning // is a 'comment', which is a request for the compiler to ignore the rest of the line. Re-compile the file with the C89 standard. What happens? Can you find an alternative way of writing a comment which works properly for the C89 standard?

Finally, look at the printf statement. What is different about it compared to the Hello World program. Change the values and see what happens. Can you find ways of doing other calculations?

Worksheet: C Syntax and Versions: Answers

Mike Fraser
Week 1

The idea was to compile this program, look at the errors and warnings from the compiler, and fix the bugs.

#include <stdioo.h>
#inclde <stdlib.h>

mian(void) {
  printf("Hello")
  printf(World);
  printf("\");
  return 0;
)

The bugs were:

The filename of the first included library is spelled incorrectly:

#include <stdioo.h>       ->      #include <stdio.h>

The keyword include on the second line is spelled incorrectly

#inclde <stdlib.h>        ->      #include <stdlib.h>

The main function, which all programs need, is spelled incorrectly

mian(void) {              ->      main(void) {

Also, strictly speaking, the return type of the main function is missing

main(void) {              ->      int main(void) {

A semicolon is missing from the end of a statement

printf("Hello")           ->      printf("Hello");

Double quotes are missing from a string constant

printf(World);            ->      printf("World");

Or, better, add a space to separate the two words when printed

printf(World);            ->      printf(" World");

The backslash character in a string is an escape character, which gives a special meaning to the following character, so \n means newline, \\ means a backslash character, and \" means an actual double quote character which is included in the string rather than closing it. So "\" is an incomplete string because it has no closing double quote. The sequence of print statements needs a newline, so the best fix is

printf("\");              ->      printf("\n");

The function is closed with a parenthesis (round bracket) rather than a brace (curly bracket)

)                         ->      }

The idea behind the second part of the worksheet was to compile this program under the C99 standard and investigate the issues. (Note in the original worksheet, the newline at the end of the printf was missing.)

#include <stdio.h>

int main(void) {
// Calculate 3*4 and print the result
    printf("3*4=%d\n", 3*4);
    return 0;
}

If the program is in a file twelve.c as suggested, the compiling command is:

gcc -std=c99 twelve.c -o twelve

One issue is that the line beginning // is a one-line comment, which is one of the additions in the C99 standard, so it gets accepted. If you compile using the C89 standard, i.e. with:

gcc -std=c89 twelve.c -o twelve

then it is not accepted. The only kind of comment accepted in C98 is the multi-line kind starting with /* and ending with */

/* Calculate 3*4 and print the result */

By the way, if you compile without specifying a standard, i.e. with gcc twelve.c -o twelve, you are compiling to the C89 standard, but with gcc-specific extensions. It is not a good idea to use compiler extensions, because then the program will probably not compile on any other C compiler. One of the main aims of a good C programmer is to produce programs which are as stable as possible, across platforms and C compilers.

Extras

Ian Holyer, 9th October

If you find the worksheet easy, or finish it quickly, you might like to try these:

Write a program which uses the sizeof function to find out how many bytes are used on the computer you are using for a value of each of these types:

char
short
int
long
long long (using the C99 standard)
float
double
char * (or any other pointer type)

Use Google to find out the different answers you might get for (a) 32 bit systems (b) 64-bit Linux (LP64) (c) 64-bit Windows (LLP64) (d) 32-bit programs running on 64-bit systems. Note: these differences can cause immense problems, even though they do not affect "fully standard-compliant" programs.

A declaration such as union u { t1 x; t2 y }; defines a type union u which allows the same memory to be used by two different types. If a variable v is declared of this type, then v.x treats v as having type t1, and v.y treats it as having type t2.

Normally, it is up to the programmer to remember how the memory is currently being used and to access it appropriately. However, it is possible to 'cheat', by storing something as type t1 and then extracting it as if it had type t2. This works if the data stored happens to form a valid value of type t2.

Write a program which uses a union type to store an int value and then examine it as an array of four bytes (chars). Store an int value of 1234 in base 256, in order to number the bytes of the int, and then find out in what order those bytes are stored in memory.

Use Google to find out about different byte orderings (little-endian, big-endian, middle-endian, bi-endian) and which common processors use which orderings.

Does it make sense to ask what order the bits of a byte are stored in?

Write a program to help find out how memory (or at least virtual memory) is laid out on the computer you are using. To do that, create pointers, re-interpret them as int or long integers, and print them out. The aim is to answer these two questions.

A C program uses three areas of memory: (a) static (for functions, constants and global data - everything the compiler knows about before the program runs), (b) the stack (for local variables declared inside functions) and (c) the heap (for lumps of memory allocated dynamically with the malloc family of functions). What order are these areas of memory allocated in?

Also, which direction does the stack go in, i.e. is new stack memory allocated by moving upwards or downwards in memory?

A quine is a program that generates and prints out its own source code (without reading from its own source file). Write a quine in C. The main trick is to define a string and use it twice.

Extras

Ian Holyer, 16th October

If you find the worksheet easy, or finish it quickly, you might like to try these:

Write a program which uses a function to print out an int in binary. There is a problem because the least significant bit has to be calculated first, but printed out last. Solve this by using an array to store the bits as you calculate them, and then print the answer out using the array.

Write another function to print out an int in binary. This time, instead of using an array, use recursion to solve the ordering problem. (The function calls itself to print out all the bits except the last, then prints the last bit.)

Get your program to print out the binary representation of a number of type float. Use either a union type or a cast to re-interpret the float as an int. You may need to allow for byte ordering issues on your computer. Make sure the answers you get agree with the examples on the main worksheet.

Write a function to convert a character from lower case to upper case (or leave it unchanged if it is not a lower case character) in the same way as the standard toupper function. Your code should not mention any ASCII character codes.

Here is a program which reads a line of text from the user and echos it back. Put it in echo.c and try it out.

#include <stdio.h>
int main() {
  int max = 10;
  char line[max];
  fgets(line, max, stdin);
  printf("%s", line);
}

Note: the array is deliberately very small, in order to check overflow issues. Note: the code uses fgets not gets because gets has bug and security dangers (and the only reason it still exists is to support old, bad code). Note: fgets is different from gets in three ways: you have to specify what stream it reads from, there is an explicit size limit, and the newline is included in the text it reads in. Note: printf calls should normally include newlines, especially when used for debugging, otherwise the text is buffered up and doesn't appear on screen at the point in the program that you expect it to, but in this case the newline is expected to be included in the string being printed. Note: the program uses the name max for the constant 10, so that 10 is mentioned only once and can be changed in one place.

Try the program three times, typing in the lines:

12345678
123456789
1234567890

Check that you understand what is happening in all three cases.

Fix up the program so that it copes with arbitrarily long lines, without increasing the size of the array or using any other storage space. Hint 1   Hint 2   Hint 3

Although the program now works, the line typed in is never available as a whole to work on. If you know how to use the malloc family of functions, which a general function to read in a line of any length from the user and return it as a string.

Extras

Ian Holyer, 23th October

If you find the worksheet easy, or finish it quickly, you might like to try these questions. They are about variable length arrays, and how they might be used to write a general matrix library. It is recommended that you compile all programs with -std=c99.

Array facilities in C were originally based on constant array sizes, so that the compiler could know the size of an array without storing the size information anywhere. The C99 standard introduced a facility for variable length arrays. Try the following:

int h=3, w=5;
int matrix[h][w];

Does this work if matrix is defined as a global, or if it is defined inside a function, or both? Answer

Answer: It only works inside a function, not globally.

Does it work if h and w are read in so that the their values cannot be known at compile time? Answer

Answer: Yes, it works even if the sizes are read in.

How do you think the compiler keeps track of the width and height of the array? Answer

Answer: The compiler stores sizes in hidden local variables in the function, in case the h and w variables change.

Do you think this is a suitable way to handle all variable-sized arrays? Answer

Answer: A big array, or lots of arrays, shouldn't be allocated like this, because the allocation may be on the function-call stack, which is often limited to catch runaway programs. Also this approach is not sufficiently flexible if the number of arrays needed in a program is unknown.

Does this feature work if you don't specify a standard, or if you specify -std=c89? Does -pedantic make a difference? Why? Answer

Answer: Yes, the feature works whether you specify no standard or -std=c89. With no standard specified, the gcc compiler supports (roughly) the C89 standard plus some early extensions of its own, and variable length arrays were an early extension, later adopted by C99. The feature also works if you specify -std=c89 -pedantic. The purpose of the -pedantic flag is to switch on all warnings required by the relevant standard. In the C89 standard, almost all extensions are explicitly allowed, and hardly any warnings are required, so -pedantic is nearly useless. The C99 standard is stricter, and so -pedantic is more useful in trying to ensure that programs stay within the standard. However, its usefulness is still very limited, and it remains very difficult to ensure that a program is properly compiler-independent.

Try writing a function like this which fills a matrix with zeros:

void fill(int h, int w, int matrix[h][w]) {
  ...
}

Is there any restriction on the ordering of the arguments? Answer

Answer: The size arguments must come before the matrix argument.

Given that C uses call-by-value, you might expect the argument variable matrix to hold a copy of the array passed in as an argument, in which case the function would have no effect. So can the function actually affect the array that is passed and, if so, why? Answer

Answer: All basic C language features produce code consisting of a couple of instructions at most. Therefore passing an array to a function, which would happen by copying, is not allowed. However, if you use code that looks as if it is passing an array to a function, the array variable is automatically replaced by a pointer to the array (or to put it another way, arrays are passed by pointer even though everything else is passed by value). So the function can affect the original array passed in.

Can you use a typedef to create an abbreviated name for the type of a (variable-sized) matrix? Answer

Answer: No. Technically, you can write a local typedef inside the function, but that's nearly useless because you can't use it in the argument list.

Try this code, for allocating space for a matrix dynamically:

int (*matrix)[w] = malloc(sizeof(int[h][w]));

What header do you need to make this work without warnings? Answer

Answer: You need #define <stdlib.h> There may be other headers which include the declaration of malloc, but this is the official one.

Is it possible to do better than this, declaring the matrix as int matrix[h][w] as before? Answer

Answer: No.

Can this matrix be indexed in the same way as one declared with int matrix[h][w]? Answer

Answer: Yes.

Can this matrix be passed to the fill function? Answer

Answer: Yes.

Now let's think about the overall design of a matrix library.

Can you write a function which allocates space for an array as in question 3 and then passes it back to the caller using the int a[h][w] style of notation? Answer

Answer: No. The standard says that a function cannot return an array.

Can you write a function which allocates space for an array as in question 3 and then passes it back to the caller using the int (*a)[w] style of notation? Answer

Answer: No, not quite. You can define a function int (*new(...))[3] {...} for example, but the width has to be a constant. There is no way to have a variable as the second dimension.

Is there a way round these problems that involves casting? Answer

Answer: You can write an allocation function as int *new(...) {...} and cast the result using int (*matrix)[w] = (int (*)[w]) new(w, h);.

Is there a way round these problems that involves re-design? Answer

Answer: You can write your functions so that the caller supplies the space for the answer. For example, a function for adding two matrices might be defined as void add(int w, int h, int m1[w][h], int m2[w][h], int sum[w][h]) { ... }.